Vasudevan Balakrishnan

Accomplished software development leader and architect with over 20 years of hands-on experience that includes analysis and design, architecture, development, and leading teams, building web, desktop, mobile, cloud-native applications and big data analytics. Passionate technologist dedicated to continuous learning and professional growth, mentoring talent, and improving development processes.

EXPERIENCE

Soros Fund Management, New York — Principal Software Lead

2009 - PRESENT

Direct oversight of both Development and DevOps teams, serve business group heads and executives. Build core business critical applications, services and data pipelines in mid/back-office space. Lead the team with design, architecture, and bring innovation by carrying out R&D / trials to evaluate and recommend products / tools.

Significant projects include:

- Build high impact real-time dashboards for executives / PM(s) accessible via desktop app and native iOS mobile app with robust features to view P&L, risk measures, exposures, drill down on data, visualizations, personalizations, and notifications.
- Build data pipelines, services, applications in mid/back-office space with continued focus on modernization micro services, containers, cloud services.
- Transformed traditional software development processes into a DevOps model, selected DevOps stack, and led implementations for JIRA, BitBucket (git), Bamboo, and Octopus Deploy.
- Leading the cloud initiative to migrate on-premise resources to Azure. Working
 with Microsoft, Internal Engineering, Networking and Cybersecurity teams to
 create a blueprint for setting up cloud resources, subscriptions, security and
 governance.
- Modernizing existing data analytics / compute platform using Databricks and Apache Spark in Azure. Identified key usage scenarios / challenges in the current environment, drove the PoC with vendor and demonstrated the new platform to key stakeholders for sponsorship.

Ivy Asset Management, New York — Senior Developer / Tech Lead

2005-2009

Led the team in design and development of core business functions - Portfolio Allocations, Liquidity Calculations, Transaction Management, Manager Exposures, Compliance Monitor, Risk Limits, Statistics, et al and backend services infrastructure.

Cognizant — Tech Lead

1996 - 2005

Provided technical leadership for development teams on multiple engagements across industry verticals – Retail banking, Hospitality, Pharmaceutical / healthcare information solutions provider.

SKILLS

- Team Leadership
- Project Management
- Architecture
- Full stack
- Big Data Analytics
- DevOps
- Mentoring

LANGUAGES

C#, Python, C++, SQL, TypeScript, HTML, R, Swift, F#

STACKS

Web (Angular) Mobile (iOS) Desktop Cloud (Azure)

PLATFORMS

Apache Spark Databricks Docker Kubernetes

EDUCATION

Masters of Computer Applications (M.C.A), Coimbatore Institute of Technology - India

Bachelor of Applied Sciences (B.Sc.), Coimbatore Institute of Technology - India